all right welcome everyone to another
awakening from the meaning crisis
discord q a tonight's guest is peter
limberg from the stoa.ca
thank you for being peter for being here
it's my pleasure thanks for inviting me
that's great you know our our
communities we've been sort of watching
a lot of our our members uh go on your
events i think probably some of your
event
members are our members here i think we
have quite a bit of overlap
in in what we're doing in our two
communities so
it's great to have you here and and
hopefully we this can be the start of
a number of collaborations uh between
our our
our two groups
[Music]
so and then something good uh and now
here i'm gonna ask you guys some
questions too because i'm here to learn
as well absolutely yeah yeah
feel free to uh to throw them out uh
whenever you'd like
uh so well let me start off though by
asking you a question you know
not everybody here is familiar with you
you know can you tell us about yourself
you know what
what was your journey what took you to
brought you to this point
uh to starting the stoa
[Music]
all right this is a good question and
i'll try to answer it in a way that
ties in how i know john as well and
i work together um
yeah so i guess when i was in the
education industry uh
learning and development and uh
as a career and there was a hunger for
philosophy the philosophize i was a
student at the university of toronto in
philosophy uh i'm 35 right now so
it's a while ago uh but i did take uh
meditation classes with john the old
school meditation classes
at the the multi-faith center which was
quite a treat and that's when i first
first met him um and so well
i can't even remember now like uh maybe
three four years ago i had that itch the
philosophical itch so i started these
these groups one of them being stoicism
toronto
which quickly became one of the largest
stove groups in the world and i'm a
practitioning stoic or at least i like
to think i am
and the other group was another
philosophical
group um called intellectual explorers
club at the time
and uh and through both these groups uh
i got some reputation in these sort of
like sense making game b
type circles because i was writing about
the culture war and the medic tribe and
stuff like that
invited john to my podcast first time i
i've seen him or spoke to him in a while
uh when we got lunch and i told him
about all these kind of conversational
modalities that i've been engaging in
like circling
and whatnot and he just got so excited
about it
because he there's an intuition there
that there was something there
and uh so went on a research project
started researching a lot of these kind
of conversational modalities like
circling
insight dialogue um restorative circles
empty circles
i introduced john to a lot of players in
this space like a guy
and then they just freaking hit it off
uh so that's kind of how i know
john and before covet happened we were
part of a bi-weekly circling group here
in toronto with taylor
um i'm authentically i think he was on
his on this
show um so that's that's how i know uh
john and so when when covet happened
my my philosophy groups i couldn't even
meet in person anymore uh
because you know you couldn't uh get me
to do social distancing
and i always had a desire to uh for a
long while now to open up a
philosophical coffee shop to house
these groups so you know our wisdom gym
ecology of practices could have uh
could be done in the physical location
um so like you know what fuck it let's
just uh
launch this online so i launched the
stoa
which is basically combining that that
more jazzy philosophical group
intellectual sports club and this dose
in toronto i combined them together
called the stoa and it became an online
event space
we have something uh like a college of
practice in our wisdom gym that that's
emerging
and we have i call it a communal podcast
it's basically like like this you know
you interview someone and then the
collective intelligence uh asks
questions to the
speaker which is great by the way
because it saves you from doing research
on your speakers you could
everyone else to do that i i love that
you know podcasting much better
um yeah it's been it's been going it's
been growing uh
there's a lot of excitement and buzz
around it i'm sure there's more i can
say on it
uh but ultimately i don't really know
what it is or where it's going either
too which kind of makes it a little bit
exciting
you've described yourself as a stoic so
maybe just for for those who don't know
what's a brief description of stoicism
stories hate describing themselves or at
least good stories dude
like or they hate describing explosives
um but
uh yeah there's something about
epictetus like this like epictetus he
was one of the
the stoics he says um explain your
philosophy embody it
i just i just love that and so i hate
hate talking about stoicism
but since you asked very nicely i will i
will answer it
um yeah stoicism was uh
i think john talked about it in his
meaning crisis series so you can refer
to that
in episode 20 or something like that um
it was an ancient
philosophy that started in ancient
greece and then migrated to ancient rome
um and it actually started in uh it's
like a the stoic okayly it was a painted
porch
that's how they got the name they were
hanging out with the stoa
and uh yeah that's what they got done in
the stoix and zeno was the original
stoic
uh but they're known more they had like
their whole cosmology that
kind of philosophy but they're they're
known uh today
for the the kind of the three roman
stoics marcus aurelius
seneca and epictetus um
and and because they they
really put emphasis on ethics roman and
the stoic ethics
and it maps over like beautifully to a
lot of uh psychological principles today
uh and i guess the
the axiomatic core of stoicism is what
they call live in accordance with nature
um and how to do that as you follow the
cardinal virtues uh
prudence practical reason um
courage uh temperance and injustice
and if you double click on the practical
reason there is they have this i'll call
them uh
lived heuristics uh like focus on
what's in your control the dichotomy of
control radically focus on what you
control and
and do not concern yourself what's not
in your control uh more fact they love
thy fate
um voluntary hardship you know like lean
into uh
um obstacles so they have this famous
line the obstacle is the way
um so i don't know if i did justice
explaining
stoicism but that's it in a nutshell
it's it's known to be like
hyper practical when i uh i took
philosophy
in university they didn't discuss
stoicism at all because it was too
practical they just had like one mention
in like the 101 class um a lot of people
like
from the group that i was running in
toronto people who tend to
uh work or operate environments with
high uncertainty like military doctors
entrepreneurs they tend to gravitate
towards stoicism
because they're like you know i'm
already doing this philosophy this is
this is putting a name to it
um so that i think uh
encapsulates what stoicism is and i'm a
little bit like
i guess i'm a little bit weird stoic um
if you read some of my journals and
writings but
that's that's sort of the core of it
actually that that's the question i was
going to ask next uh that you've just
brought up you i think i've seen you
describe yourself as an
unconventional stoic so what is what
does that mean to you
yeah maybe it's like a sloppy stoic
maybe that's a little bit better
uh someone who um is not always
congruent with principles um that's not
not true that's not true
let me let me think i guess like the
proselytizers of stoicism they call them
the modern stoicism movement and guys
like donald robinson
uh massimo uh ryan holiday
um they don't really kind of play in the
sandbox that
a lot of us play in with uh
metamodernism the meaning crisis game b
and so i guess i'm like i have a foot
and strong resonance in this world uh
and then i have a foot the stoic world
too but most people who
talk or write about social have no idea
what's going on here so i guess that's
why
i'm sort of like the black sheep of the
modern stoic community because they
don't the fuck i'm talking about half
the time when i'm talking about like you
know game b
your meaning crisis and stuff like that
um so that's why i kind of like
self-describe myself as a little bit of
a
stoic weirdo but yeah and then the one
thing too
that's what it is is that
this the you know there's like a lower
case statism
or like the dictionary definition of
stoicism where you like repress your
emotions you don't you don't you kind of
like you don't share
what's really what's really bothering
you and then there's like stoicism
you know the uppercase sources and which
is the actual philosophy of it
and a lot of people have this
misunderstanding i think it's very fair
why they have this is that
you know stoics are these emotionless
creatures that
you know like they don't express
anything but it's like if you read
journals or if you interact with me i'm
like a fucking emotional basket case i'm
just articulating
what i i feel is most alive for me and
these conversational modalities that you
know john and
guy the guy has developed circling it's
all about that
um and i think what's really beautiful
about stoicism is uh there's there's
something called cognitive diffusion
that the
acceptance commitment therapy talks
about it's basically
like creating distance between you and
your emotional realities
uh so you don't get like a mesh with
them so you're not hijacked by them so
you're not reacting
from them stoicism is a beautiful
operating system
if you follow it uh loyally they create
that cognitive diffusion um
but that's just step one in my opinion
step two is like turning around looking
at the emotions and then building a
relationship with them learning from
them what are they trying to tell you
treat them as friends giving you advice
and friends always give the best advice
but you can learn something from them um
so that's sort of stoicism that i like
to
i like to talk about and do so if
if someone wanted to start following
becoming more of a stoic
do they need to do thousands of hours of
research of reading
everyone from marcus aurelius to zeno
and
and beyond or what would you suggest to
them if they wanted to start applying
this in their day-to-day life
yeah take a cold shower 100 cold showers
and whip yourself while you do it
no um yeah
like i don't really care about
identifying or calling myself a stoic
but if you're if you
gravitate towards anything i said or the
stoic meme or the stoic philosophy i
definitely recommend
reading um epictetus his handbook
i read marcus aurelius meditation read
seneca read the big three stoics
you can read some entry level guys like
um ryan holiday is good
uh so just do like read up on stoicism
it's not that difficult that the kind of
the summary i gave is basically what
they're gonna say maybe with
with some more nuance um
and the thing that i kind of like about
stoicism is
there's different techniques of how to
practice it like donald robinson
uh here's an exercise called the view
from above and john actually when the
the store conference i i
i had her in september i don't know if
you were there brett but in september
had a stoacon
uh conference john was there and he did
he talked about the view from above
and it was a really really awesome
conversation and then donald actually
did the exercise
afterward um and this is basically kind
of doing a visualization where you
picture yourself going above yourself
going above the world and then kind of
giving yourself some some distance from
it so
you have that perspective and they have
exercises like voluntary hardship um
where you take cold showers i use tickle
showers every day i stop actually
it's really hot so i just take them it's
kind of easy right now
and then like daily uh meditations
writing to yourself every day
like i do i write to myself every day
i've been doing it for over 100 days now
since covet happened so they have
various exercise
exercise exercises to to kind of follow
but it is um
there's no regimen there's no like
there's no like the lineage is is
was broken you know it's not like some
lineages of buddhism orthodox
christianity where you can kind of see
how they practice you have mentors in
the individual system there
um no they don't have that we're a lot
of these modern authors are just kind of
guessing how they practice like a little
bit from above
journaling and stuff like that your head
was really great for this
um but this is why i kind of like
stoicism because you get to be a little
entrepreneurial there
you can kind of see you know take that
kind of that skeleton philosophy
reinvent it so it's not terribly
dogmatic these days
exactly there might be some people who
are dogmatic about it but it's like
there's no agreement
of like of how it should be practiced or
how it was practiced even
so so yeah you you mentioned you you
journal and i i came across
uh your uh your your letters
or on on what's the site letter.wiki
uh is that is that your is that the
journal you're talking about or do you
do that and you also have your own
private journal as well yeah that was
the
that's where i started out i did it for
like 94 days there and then i
went over to sub stack and that's where
they are right now
so so you're you're not just journaling
you're journaling for everyone you're
you're putting it out there
these aren't your private journals you
you want people to see
yes uh but i'm i'm really trying to
write to myself
doing it which is kind of like a little
bit weird because you know other people
are reading it i don't know who exactly
is reading it
but i do get myself in a state where i
am writing to myself in order to
remind myself of these these truths that
i hold
and and what what so you've done this
now for a hundred days
have you noticed any transformative
effects in yourself from doing this what
what does it afford to do
would you say um
yeah it was really good man
it's really really been good uh it's
actually my favorite part of the day
waking up being an espresso just pumping
up the journal
um and it's an it's an exercise to just
be radically truthful too that's what i
find
um because that's what the stoics and a
lot of other people believe is that the
better off of philosophy before you get
to all the nitty gritties is
is the capacity to be truthful mapping
over your work to what you believe to be
true in reality
and this is just another form of that
and it helps slow down my thinking
uh and it helps process like the
emotional realities the pains the hurts
the confusions that i'm going through
it's been really really helpful to do
that
and i've been privately journaling i
gotta have probably over like a hundred
thousand hours of
private journaling uh they used to do
like the artist uh
way morning pages exercises you just
kind of
just write to yourself reassociation
style in the morning that
really helps kind of processing it's
like circling what i really like about
circling
is you're mapping your words to your
reality your felt sense reality
uh and so you can kind of like separate
what your thoughts are what your story
your narrative is
to the emotional reality that it is
coming up so you're not kind of
conflating the two
and journaling really helps with that
i've been doing it privately
for for years i just deleted them right
after uh just to have no records so just
like really raw
and so that kind of spirit that practice
of writing raw to myself i'm carrying it
over in a public format
shifting a little bit because i'm having
kind of a you know a little bit
impression management
and but with my meta awareness i'm aware
of that pressure management so it has
kind of an interesting
interaction was wondering do you find
yourself being a little less radically
honest
when it's out there i mean there are
things probably
we don't want to show to other people
has that shifted from your private
writing to your public writing um
no not really uh because i'm still i
would say i'm
just as honest but i'm i'm
[Music]
selective about what i'm honest about
right i'm using my discernment like okay
this is like
not prudent to you know be honest about
this thing but
if i am going to speak about something
i'm going to kind of put myself to my
edge of it and if i find like there's a
barrier there like oh what's going on
here then i can explore that
so so you talk a lot about the meeting
crisis and you have this uh great white
paper
that you did a couple years ago with uh
sorry who did you you wrote it with
connor
yes with uh with connor and uh
you you talk about six different crises
uh and i'll i'll try to post the uh i'll
post a link in a bit to the
in the event uh text at the end of this
uh to
to this white paper uh so this this you
run 2018 and you talk about six
different crises including the meaning
crisis and you have the reality crisis
the belonging crisis the proximity
crisis
the sobriety crisis and the warfare
crisis now we focus obviously mostly on
the meaning crisis
what does the meeting crisis mean to you
and i guess i would ask you
are you sort of on board with john's
view of the meaning crisis or do you
diverge from him
in any ways or are are you basically on
the same page with
john on on the meeting crisis yeah like
uh i would say um
i'm pretty would have from what i know
with john
um that's out there i'm pretty on the
same page with him when it comes to the
meaning crisis
um i might not understand all of it but
but
it's pretty congruent of it and this is
the paper came out
uh before john did his youtube series in
the meeting crisis
and um i think i came across the term
readings on uh john chris's zombie book
um so i didn't know they declined it at
the time i just thought it was something
that was in the air
uh when we put it in this this white
paper
now now in in this white paper and maybe
you could talk a little bit about it but
you you're careful careful not to give
too many prescriptions at the end i mean
a lot of it's sort of a description of
what what you've
witnessed going on with you know with
the left right with the
with tribalism with trump and all the
different groups out there from the far
left to the far right
um and you make some suggestions in
terms of
sort of ecology of practice type
suggestions but
do you see a way out of from the meaning
crisis or first maybe give a brief
description of how you see the meeting
crisis and
what how what you think we can do about
it
uh and maybe where the stoa fits into
that
yeah yeah that's good uh where's the
chat how do i how do i share things with
this thing
yeah so so right above the event hall uh
recording there's event text
and so you can you can uh put anything
in in there
oh shit kyra has a question to me about
the dark store
don't pick her okay so the uh um
so for those of you maybe i'll explain
the white paper first and then give it
to the your unique
uh crisis question um
yeah so the original idea if you see on
the
top uh the chat there's like the
spreadsheet and then the spreadsheet
there's a list of these
memetic tribes uh and then some of them
you might
might have heard of like social justice
activists or the social justice warriors
black lives matter
v2 um critical gender critical feminists
which are
the turfs that's what they're called now
if you scroll down to the more
reactionary tribes
um uh you've got nanosphere
in cell uh alt-right you've got some
conspiratorial tribes like humanon and
you got more centrist tribes like
intellectual dark web
this was 2018 that this was created
today
you know game b would be on here maybe
john would even have his own tribe i
don't know what it would be called
so the idea is with this paper was to
kind of present the culture war instead
of like this
um kind of like you know this bipolar
affair with
left and right you know if you watch fox
or cnn
that's what you're going to get it's
like a a
war between the the left and the right
but we we we made the argument
that uh the culture right now is a
multi-polar war
it's a war between these memetic tribes
people who
get kind of tribal almost an
addictive sense around certain ideas
certain memes that they share on these
social media platforms
and you know there's no if you kind of
look at the alt light and the alt-right
are fighting against each other
um social justice activists are fighting
against the
the turfs um that dirtbag left is
fighting as a social justice act
everyone's kind of fighting as a social
justice activist but all these these
kind of tribes are fighting
um against themselves and they're having
these odd alliances
and the idea was just to create the
spreadsheet and then we said you know
what let's just fucking try to
explain why this came about and so we
went through the meeting crisis and all
this type of stuff
um and i i view this this this sort of
white paper as like a psychoactive drug
when you kind of read it when you kind
of see the spreadsheet like oh shit like
if you're not aware of the stuff like um
most people are probably aware of it in
this space
but it was sort of like it jogs you out
of your your kind of like
tribal warring reality tunnel so that
was sort of like the point of it um
how i see stoa in this
uh i like the idea of being um the
switzerland
of the culture war in a way we're
a place where we're not combatants we're
not like fighting
like with memes on social media but
we're trying to figure out how to become
embodied tribes uh so wait
move away from memetic tribes and to
become embodied tribes
and the part of the project is to seduce
a lot of these mimetic tribalists
to the store or places like it uh like
this discord
and learn how to become embodied through
a developing ecology of practices
and then i think you know things like
circling and all these different kind of
meditative um
practices breath work practices really
help with that
i don't know what the formula is for it
i was sort of like i'm in a cowboy
discovering phase on it
but that's sort of the idea develop what
i'm using the term
wisdom gym and ecology of practices and
then
have at least the capacity to become
body drives
well so you mentioned kira sakira why
don't you
put your question to to peter i said
don't pick
carragher
that was the request all right
bring it on very good um okay
so i've actually been wanting to reach
out to you and ask you about this so i
i was like oh this is a great
opportunity i can ask this question
can you put some context around what
what prompted you to
to bring pat ryan onto the stoa and
you know give him give him a platform
for
you know his presentations and the dark
stoa
i mean you can just explain what what
the dark stoa is
do you want to explain it or do you want
me to point it
i can give it a shot and then you can
fill in the blanks um so the dark stoa
is a group that meets on friday nights
and there's a guy pat ryan
uh the tag line that has been given to
him is the most dangerous man on the
internet
um and i would say
what you gave him that name guy gave him
the nickname
and um he essentially is
giving his frame for
the meeting crisis for where he thinks
the world is going
and it takes you to some very dark
twisted places
that's the best description i've got for
it
yeah um so
it's uh uh how the how he phrased it is
existential ultra catastrophes
uh exploring existential ultra
catastrophes for the sole purpose of
refraining them into
um same pathways that you can navigate
and
have action and meaning from it um so
that's sort of like the
thing and he he's just like this wild
man uh
he's a genius he's like he's incredibly
intelligent
um not university educated he's
homegrown
as a hacker he's involved in cultural
happenings like putting milo
yiannopoulos on the map
or at least he claims um so he's he
he's just dangerous kind of knowing the
guy and then putting him on the the
store
uh how he got my radar uh basically
jordan hall emailed me
hey you know patrick ryan i'm like no
and then then i
sent me the website and i started
reading about him and i'm like shit
what this guy is saying is true this is
this is pretty fucked up and dark
uh half the stuff i didn't understand
but i'm always intrigued by
i can i can kind of sniff out an
original thinker like i'm always
intrigued by one
um burton peterson was my therapist i
don't know if i mentioned that to you
but before he he was my therapist um
before we went over the culture we're
seeing wait wait so you had
you had john as your teacher and
peterson as your therapist
yes yes it's a double what the double
whammy there
um wow that um but when
before jordan peterson went the culture
were um you know
warrior type mode uh um i was he was my
therapist for about two years
and but before that um you know he had
like this indie rock
like intellectual cred about him right
like if you're into intellectual space
that you're aware of him but no one else
knew about him
but you could tell he's a fucking
original thinker right and so like i
sniffed them out like i got to know this
guy
same thing with john right john the
original mind
i want to know him same thing with pat
ryan right basically i don't understand
someone on first blush and i can't kind
of like
categorize them into like one of those
spreadsheet lines and like a medic tribe
you know they're someone's original
thinker
so um yeah i got to know pat
uh jordan hall put me on his radar i
read him like oh my god invite him to my
podcast
had a bunch of conversations with him
privately um and then maybe
despite my better judgment i invited him
on to do a session
uh friday nights the dark stoa and
they've been very popular very fun very
edgy
you can all check it on the youtube
channel the darks the dark stoa
it's hard to track but it's probably uh
best to start with the first one
yeah i don't know if that answers your
question kyra but i really like the guy
dangerous but i like him i guess maybe
the follow-up question would be how did
like how do you now that you've gotten
to know him how do you
where would you put him because yeah
that i had encountered him like a year
and a half ago
and so when he started showing up on the
dark so i was like
okay like my he had been on my radar too
for the same reason and so i was just
curious where
where he fits in in your map now
um yes he definitely has a reactionary
um fight to him uh for sure
um temperamentally and uh
yeah there's the the he's into
which is a more sophisticated way of
saying conspiracies
[Music]
from a very first principle approach
so there's that kind of like that that
constellation going on there
uh but he's also plugged into the game b
space he was danish market burger he
knows jordan hall he knows jim rott
peter wang knows all those players
i don't think he's come across um gone
yet
um talked to alexander bard
but yeah he's uh he's a very collective
thinker
but he is more more reactionary at least
temperamentally i would say
thanks on the subject of the dark story
you write about your your damon
uh is that maybe you could tell us a
little bit about
what you mean by that and the importance
of that concept
yeah um so the daemon or the diamond
i really want to pronounce it i don't
know uh
i got it from like socrates essentially
he said that uh
it is daemon is his guiding spirit um
you know and the way i hold it if you
want to like articulate it in secular
terms
it's uh like a certain quality of
intuition that says go here
and you don't know why it's saying go
here but when you listen to it
there's like no guarantee either if you
go there um so this is gonna be a
victory but if you go there
like delicious things happen um so
for example like me wanting to see
peterson as a client
befriending john he started the podcast
we started the stoa you write that white
paper all these are like daemon
kind of like impulses they weren't
didn't come from first principle
thinking
you know they got like the the prudence
check after the fact but
what kind of like nudged me there was a
certain quality of intuition that was
quite different
than other intuitions is not like a
hedonistic thing it's not like um
desire to dominate or anything like that
so
that's how i personally hold uh the demo
and then the you know the greeks they
have something called eudemonia which a
lot of
modernists translate into happiness but
if you just unpack the word it means
being in right relationship with your
demon
being right relationship with that
guiding spirit that quality of intuition
um yeah that's how i
uh hold the dame on and then i imagine
you you
you i think you created this discord
right and you're you're organizing as a
passion
well a passion project i imagine there's
some demonic kind of energy going on
there
yeah as you were as you were describing
it it felt very similar to
to what was going on with me well as i
was listening to
john's awakening from the meeting crisis
and and the
the instinct that there's something
important going on here that i don't
know if it'll work
but i think there's something worth
trying and worth and i wanted
to be a part of it to help make it
happen uh yeah
so now now now of course the would you
say i mean our instincts can lead us in
the wrong direction too would you say
that's different than our daemon that
they're
the daemon is our the good instincts and
the but then there's the
the not so good instincts and how do you
tell the how do you tell the difference
then how do you tell when it's your
demon versus
leading you in the wrong direction and
you're stray
right um yeah uh
uh i can just speak for myself when i
sort of
live in such a way where i'm listening
and following
this um kind of intuitive instinct
uh it leads to good places uh but you
can interpret it
you know what it's telling you um and
you can do your ego can get in the way
you can have narcissistic qualities and
kind of like bachelor eyes like
interpretation of what those are trying
to tell you or where to go
tell you where to go and this is why i
think it's like having an ecology of
practice is where you can
practice reasoning you know you do your
syllogisms you practice how to reason
well
you um you meditate you do breath work
you have good
friends that can keep you in check so
you're you're in dialogue dialogues with
them
uh dialogues with them so yeah i i think
if you're just uh running with this kind
of energy
by itself without kind of getting help
from these other kind of psycho
technologies and you can be
you could lead you astray for sure well
you've mentioned a bit about your
ecology or practices uh so you've
mentioned circling
uh i think meditation practices what
what is your ecology of practices
um drinking espressos too many espressos
that's one uh yeah um
let's see so waking up early
uh doing uh
journaling taking cold showers
uh fitness exercises and
i would say kind of conversational
modalities like circling um
[Music]
close friends uh and then and then i
would say some breath work exercises i
haven't been doing that much lately
but that's pretty much it right now uh i
want to ramp it up and be a little more
sophisticated with it and a part
of this journey of the stoa is
investigating these and having sort of a
house though as a psycho technology
incubator where people can kind of test
out
different practices that can be you know
reported on a zoom channel and that
could be replicated and scaled up
mark you have a question
yeah peter i was wondering about you
know you're talking about the stoic as a
place to
sort of explore and uh
uh go into detail with these ecologies
of practices
and i was curious as to what those were
and if you're sort of taking any
ecologies
from stoicism uh just because i'm
unfamiliar with
you know what they had in terms of
ecologies of practice
right it seems to be all mine stuff um
and and how that plays into your
to your mission with the stoa mm-hmm
um so
uh as i mentioned to brett earlier that
you know the the
modern stoic authors they teased out
because first of all
there was still a text like i think 90
of them went missing so we don't really
know much
about like a lot of the details the
nitty-gritty of the stoics and the
lineage as dead like there was no like
living stoics that kind of like existed
from ancient rome to now um so
the ecology of practices that a lot of
the modern stoics mention
like you know voluntary hardship uh the
journaling
um the view from above they're just sort
of teasing them out
of the text and there's there's not like
a consensus or a complete agreement of
what they are
so i'm not really concerned about uh
about that and kind of bringing that
forth to the
the stoa and it's sort of a bait and
switch like the stoa is is stewarded or
run by a stoic but
the majority of our events like 90 99 of
them are not above stoicism i don't
really i don't before
talking about stoicism um that being
said
uh how to discover an ecology of
practices within the wisdom gym
right now i'm just being um a total
cowboy to be quite frank
about it i'm just listening to my dame
on what kind of practices i want to
experiment test out and want to have
reoccurring
in the gym and people are reaching out
to me uh wanting to come
um so uh right back
who did collective presenting uh she
invented that practice and it's like a
circling-esque
practice a wee space type practice she
has she comes in every friday and does
that
um we have a few other reefs-based
practitioners coming in
i don't know if people are familiar with
space but it's an integral theory term
for
these conversation authentic
conversational modalities uh that help
with
coherence um see a lot of people are
reaching out to me to come
bestowa so right now i'm just listening
and experimenting
um but there is my hope is um
i'm a junk researcher at john's uh
wisdom consciousness studies lab as well
the hope is is once we do all these
experimentations we can actually do
legitimate studies on this
yeah that's great okay so so you're
you're still you're doing the
experimentation
uh as well and this is a way to
experiment sort of in the real world
while involving other people
yeah 100 like you know there's a lot of
people that just kind of like have this
ready-made
curriculum like well you do this right
like come on
like right now i think we need to just
uh practice and experiment
uh wildly in in this space
and i kind of like this this term vince
um
horn came up with the inga that's what
you guys call it right here you have the
sangha section
yes i don't know if i'm pronouncing that
right yeah he called it like
the meta sangha uh that there needs to
be a medicine again someone said oh this
always a good example of a medisanga
and i'm like okay what does that mean so
i looked it up transformed coined it
and it essentially um a place where
kind of multiple ecology of practices
can exist so you can have like you know
a dui approach that calls you practices
where like i imagine like the star or
someplace like it they could have like
hundreds of different psychotechnologies
coexisting in this wisdom gym and then
people can kind of come in and
experiment which which ecology works for
them
there might be different ecologies that
work like the best college of the
practice might be the one that gets you
the next
um so i i don't think we should um
focus on solidifying just one getting
that one right just kind of
experimenting i think
more is the merrier right now so we can
kind of test the different combinations
dave you had a question
oh that was not a fully serious question
but um
kind of is i mean i also have a damon i
would say
from 15 years can you hear me
yes yeah we can hear you oh yeah yeah so
peter nice to meet nice to um see you
here uh
yeah and i guess it's just interesting
what is a damon where does it come from
uh how do you conceptualize it that's
something to think about
um for me has been and um i think it's
interesting but certainly i would say
that i have a damien which
likes you know socrates it stops you
doing something um
that you're about to do um as a kind of
felt sensation
in um sort of my head area
anyway that's quite personal but uh
uh yeah so that's not really a question
there but just um
what are your questions how can your
damon be more intelligent than you
that was that was my little throwaway
question in the chat uh
so yeah you have to be happy to go on
that but basically i just want to say
thank you peter
though it's mate is amazing um
unfortunately time
zones mean i can't participate which is
a real shame i'm hoping rebel wisdom
will be
um something maybe even slightly similar
wonder whether uh patrick you know
whether you can help that make that
happen
so if you want to yeah talk about that
or the damon please do
um yeah like uh uh
i saw you uh looked at the chat he said
the socrates his name one said that like
all them things not to do which is which
is true uh socrates day one
said you know told not to do things or
where
the way i'm holding it is telling me to
do things more or less than not when we
do things
uh to answer your question about how is
it more intelligent i don't know i would
i would like to uh
source the group uh for any suggestions
on that one
uh and rebel wisdom does i used to be
the community manager briefly for rebel
wisdom and they they are
also working on a wisdom gym so um
i really love seeing these different
communities pop up like this one rebel
wisdom
the emerge network for the stoa they're
doing quite similar things
and you know it's like let's put our
money where our mouth is we're going to
practice these principles of
the game beat principles of
collaboration coordination stuff like
that
and i think we can and that's why you
know i'm here
topher you had a question
are you there topher do you want me to
read it for you
all right i will read different over hi
peter we actually have a mutual friend
named
narian hopefully we cross paths sometime
soon
my question would be and forgive me if
this is explicitly included in your
paper
does the way the memetic tribes mean
plexus they're struggling for territory
online remind you of the way
the brain develops where circuits
gradually build
through a positive feedback
reinforcement process
i never really thought about that uh
it's an interesting
uh comparison i do like the idea
of um kind of like the
the internet uh the interconnected
aspects of the hardware aspect is sort
of like brain that is forming
and then uh the memes that are flowing
through it are the noaa sphere you know
the collective mind
is sort of the mind of of our collective
and currently we're like uh collectively
the whole argument of the culture war
2.0 paper was like we're
in the collective state of like
schizophrenia all these different kind
of realities hitting each other
um but maybe schizophrenia is the wrong
way to look at it maybe we're just like
you know
a four-month uh baby at this point
trying to
figure out what is what um so i do like
these brain mind analogies but um
i'll leave that to someone else to kind
of figure it to get right
and you've talked about your
experimentation i i saw that
you've been experimenting with what
you've called the communitas prayer
can you tell us about that yeah just
basically something i made up with uh
my mentor andrew tagart so andrew tagart
i don't know if you guys are familiar
with him he had a conversation with guy
and a few other people in the space
he's a practical philosopher i call him
like the sockies of the internet
uh and during many of my dark night of
the souls
i reached out to him and we had
philosophical conversations
and when the stall first started uh we
kind of leaned on our experience
experimenting with all these different
uh wee space conversational modality
technologies and then
we we did something called the community
prayer um and it
we just kind of took some of the
neighboring constraints
from like circling these different kind
of practices and created our own
uh and someone was in the hot seat they
kind of
spoke on the issue that was most
existentially salient for them
for a brief time and the collective
group gave support
just kind of spoke what wanted to be
wanted to be spoken
uh and kind of like the demonic way um
it was quite beautiful some some kind of
didn't land some were really great
but that was the experiment of doing a
community sprayer and oddly enough
a lot of people that were practitioners
in wee space came across the stowa
because we started putting that out
there so
we called it the community invitation so
i guess we invited people who are
actually practicing this stuff to come
find the stoa which is quite cool
uh pedro you have a question
uh yeah thanks brett hi peter
you referred breath work
as one of the practices you do and
my question is what is the contribution
you
expect from it is it to induce a
calm mind state or an activated one
what is its place in the stoic mindset
have you i'm curious have you ever done
a breath work or wim hof method or
anything like that
i have never done it so
this is i think the plug and uh so uh
yeah at the
store we have something called the stoic
breath uh it's uh
three times uh a week and they're all in
the morning too so if you're in in
europe i imagine you can get it
um next one i think it's sunday at 10
a.m
this is a wim hoff uh trainer he was
trained under wim hof
and he's basically doing wim hof breath
work a little bit moderate
modifications on it with kind of a stoic
framing and
the you know i i'm not too educated on
all the benefits of it but if you
experiment with it it's quite awesome uh
it really makes you feel alive
uh it puts you in your body and um
yeah it's just focusing on the breath to
bring that fire in the belly but i
recommend experimenting with it and then
and reading up on it
do you meditate as well sorry i'm sorry
go ahead oh you were just thinking thank
you for
for your for your actually i felt the
invite to
to participate so i'm gonna look
forward to it cool man
thanks yeah thank you and
i know i don't meditate brett
you could join us in the mornings uh for
our uh for our meditation saying that
uh where we meditate yeah of course
well you you said you had some questions
for us did you want to uh
throw out a few yeah
um so maybe just like uh how'd you start
like maybe just at the basics right now
like how'd you start how much members
you have
and kind of like yeah how would you be
your elevator pitch for this place
because
i've popped in twice and had to look
around i'm not familiar with discord so
i just felt like you know
overwhelmed but anything give me like an
elevator pitch of what's happening here
sure so the way we started was well i i
came across
uh some guys or who one guy who had met
on twitter
and he introduced me some guys he was
working with one
one is uh is tyler who's well he was
here now but i think he
i think he he logged off now he's our
admin and this uh
guy john buck and they were doing a
podcast
uh weekly youtube podcast on on the
beverage channel
uh going through john's awakening for
the meeting crisis so they were just at
week seven
when i when i met them and i started
doing this weekly
podcast with them where we watched an
episode or two or three and we discussed
it every week
so going through it and and at the end
uh
we interviewed john and so got to ask
him some questions and after that
i've been thinking about this for a
while how could i be involved it seemed
like a
an important project and and pitched
this discord
that involved a bunch of discord and i
thought you know yeah this
this guy needs a discord you know this
community needs a discord
so he loved the idea and uh we started
it so we started it in uh
mid to the end of april i think april
23rd now we've grown you know we've got
over a thousand members now no of course
not everyone some people join discord
and then they
they they never come back but we have a
pretty active community so
we we've got we we have we have a
a big focus on ecology practices so we
a lot of a number of us meet in the
morning for meditation we started
introducing yoga before that
we started we just started actually this
week
running john's deo logos practice
we've got one of our members has been
leading tai chi
so we do the movement practice with john
uh as well as
as well as the meditation uh we're
experimenting with rituals sort of
secularized rituals and you know
embodiment rituals rituals so just like
you sort of experimenting in the space
trying to come up with new rituals we
have a bunch of different
ch so there are a lot of people who
focus on voice and there are other
people who focus on
text uh we've got a bunch of people uh
who are working on sort of
laying out the religion that's not a
religion what it might look like
they have a document uh that's pinned in
in one of those threads uh that's sort
of
starting to map it out uh
so you know we we we bring a lot of
john's guests from the voices with
vervekey on so
so following the voices with for veki uh
i'll invite the guest here and we do a q
a similar to this so
sort of this bridge between what john's
doing on the youtube channel and the
and the uh and and the community so
really we're trying to
build like my goal is to build a
community around this awakening from the
meeting crisis
to you know help people do these
uh to put in place in ecology of
practices
to help support each other uh you know
help help people maintain
these practices and figure out each of
our own ways out of this
meaning out of the meeting crisis and
and and as well as
maybe you know you know ideally it would
be a hub for the various communities
uh that are working around uh
awakening for the meeting prices you
know groups like yours
kelly there's you know there's a jordan
hall there's all sorts of different
communities like you've said that have
been developing
you know i'd love to see this sort of as
a place where people can intermingle and
discuss ideas
you know in real time and share ideas
and collaborate
and communicate and really you know work
on dialogues
and so you know there's there so there's
i'll stop there
that's the elevator pitch cool cool and
how what's the mechanism
like do um what's the mechanism
to uh like have a practice
go into your college of practices is
someone recommend it is there like a
let's get sign off somewhere like how
does that work well i mean we're taking
a lot of
we're taking a lot of i mean guidance
from john a lot of you know so the
meditation we're we're mostly following
his but just like
like you said you know you know it's not
a dogmatic
uh practice so you know we say you know
if you have your own meditation practice
for example do that
you know you know there's just something
about you know we'll meditate together
and then we'll talk about it afterwards
with things like uh yoga and tai chi and
all that we're sort of experimenting you
know we're
with yoga we're experimenting with
different just youtube videos for now
uh just finding ones you know beginner
beginner yoga videos for people to do
uh with the dialogues we've sort of
taken his uh
you know his john's uh
the one you know the the one you know
similar to what john did on yours and he
talked about with guys in stock so
this protocol uh the the four-person
protocol
uh we the
yeah so so so we're but it it's
it's more about encouraging people to
have an ecology
of practice you know you know for him
we've been doing group lectio divina
uh which john introduced in awakening
for the meeting crisis and in his
meditation series he taught sort of a
version of lectio divina you know this
uh sort of
meditative uh embodiment style reading
uh that we've been doing as a group uh
we've got
uh i mean we have we have people uh
doing circling type authentic relating
type events as well
uh so so basically trying to hit hit
all of the uh the bases we we've
we're experimenting with ecstatic dance
which i think i've seen
you guys doing on on your on your group
as well so i think there's probably a
lot of overlap in the i
i i've noticed uh what i've looked at
your list
a lot of things you're doing are similar
to things we're doing but you know
different takes on them which is
probably a good
contrast
yeah that's pretty cool man um and i'm
glad that uh
you know john has a home now for like
his ideas have a home now here
uh because a lot of people were touching
on it like bro was not future thinkers
you know
myself but it's good that his kind of
ideas can be fully explored
here with the community that actually
watched all 50 videos
which is a feat in itself it's a rite of
passage
that's that's a psycho technology
watching jon's um 50th lectures
yeah yeah yeah for sure and there is a
group that that is going through
uh on sat on sundays uh going through
all the lectures
uh yoshio you have a question
hey uh yeah thanks hi peter um
good talk about it yeah i just wanted to
follow up
on um what brett was mentioning about
uh the differences or the similarities
about what's going on here and just
as an observer having participated in a
bunch of storm events previously
and like i i think what i've realized
about this
doa is there's something specifically
sacred in it in the way that it's
shrined up in a zoom call it has a
specific time
nobody you know you don't know ahead of
the zoom call who's going to be in there
as
as part of the audience and then uh you
know boom you're in
it it's it's very intense and then and
then
and then you know it's it's over and
then you're out and there's no
um uh there's no reception to
mingle with the with the audience and
i don't mean it as a criticism but i
think one of the reasons for
things like the discord to emerge
um is partly in response for this
this feeling of wanting to commune with
the community the audience
in in various ways both you know
formally
by being able to rehearse or practice or
develop these psycho technologies or
these ecology practices but also just to
shoot the shit
and just to figure out who we are you
know
um so i i guess that's part of
just a comment but also to pose a
question
to maybe both of you guys is
are there specific um
outcomes that you guys are noticing
based on the structure
of the technology for so for example
peter you mentioned that you had a stoic
group in toronto you guys met
face-to-face is there anything
specifically different about
what the stillweb platform on zoom is
affording is there something that you're
hacking
in the zoom feature that that it's
affording you something and
and likewise to bread is there something
about the discord
format the structure of it that is
affording
something particular that we're that
we're after
and and i'm assuming that there's a
difference between zoom and discord
and and and i keep wanting to know
you know what what is that difference
and and
so thanks
this guy has so much good questions i
love uh
um when it comes to the store want me to
go first right
uh i mean uh with with discord and
one thing well first that this that
distinguishes discord from say
twitter or facebook is the fact that
there's
video and voice seamless with the
chatting and i think that it makes a
little more personal a little more real
that you're not just chatting it's easy
to get
uh fairly toxic you know when when all
you're doing is
talking through text but once you add
video and voice
it makes the other person much more real
and that's similar to zoom
uh you know the fact that people can go
in and out uh
of discord is something i really like
you know you've you've got
i mean there's a bunch of different
discords uh too you know you you've got
the coffee house discord you've got
weinstein's discord you know there
there's there's a lot of overlap so
people can sort of see what what they
want
they can sort of be in in a similar area
and they can see what's going on in
their discords and come in and out
and you can just pop on you know one
advantage discord has over
over say zoom is you know you've got a
lot more of
the casual conversations that just pop
up where people just want to have a
conversation so they
pop into a voice channel and just talk
where zoom
is more more you have to have a planned
event with an invite
uh uh and whatnot but but zoom is great
i mean for example for psyc
for doing things like deal logos where
you can just
have all your people and then divide
them into however many rooms you want
with a click of a button that's that's a
big advantage
that zoom has over discord just a lot
harder
you really have to just manually create
a bunch of rooms to do that here on
discord
so so and we view zoom two sometimes
so we sort of meet here and then
sometimes move to zoom so depending on
what we're
what we're doing
so uh yeah i'll answer this question
then
i have to have to go but uh
yeah i'll size that the zoom discord
thing but uh i think i'll go
into the question the spirit of what
you're trying to get at there
um so when i started the store i
had a like a policy like no social media
there's no discord
no facebook no reddit uh disabled all
the
youtube comments yeah i threw up the q a
the podcast that i just they got rid of
everything and she's on the zoom channel
it's people can private message
um and there is like you're gesturing
towards there's kind of like that almost
like a sacred quality there's a kind of
like a weird silence
but there's that maybe that lack of kind
of like shooting the shit element
um that uh discord could afford um
and maybe it's the wrong move maybe
we'll start at discord eventually and do
things like that
but i am there's a distrust i have
towards it
um these type of formats
in the sense that it can turn into a
shit show uh it can get
medically hijacked by certain romantic
tribes um
you see that in the game b forums on
facebook uh and maybe this one is
protected because it has good
stewardship
or it's like so localized around john's
stuff you're only gonna get geeky super
users that like
know about the thing so it may be cool
here but but the stoa
is much broader in its scope and
especially the project of memetic
mediation
where we're inviting people from we're
writing like queer anarchists to like
you know
jack murphy to pat ryan like we have a
slew
of people come in here at the stowa and
then they're going to bring their
audiences
in and if um i just
when i have a just thought of having a
space on it i just think it will get
kind of a medically messy
and when that cultural noise will come
in especially if the project is
pneumatic mediation
i've been hesitant about doing it so far
maybe for that reason that's
the reason why i disabled all the
comments um
and also another uh tyranny of
structuralism
there's this term as a feminist term
where it can like group things can just
hijack a space
and um yeah so i'm cautious about having
that there even though there's like so
much benefits like these things are
again at the emerging um but with the
stoa there's so much activities there's
so much kind of like communities
bursting
out of it like uh um you know metagame
mastermind they have their own slack
group other campfires emerging from it
that's sort of the idea
of the space is that it's kind of like
this weird entity that things can
be born from it but it's it doesn't have
any kind of focalized point there
especially on social media
um yeah so i don't know if that answered
your question that's currently my
my thought on the matter and i could be
totally wrong to be a mistaken
approach to it but i'm not sold on on on
having a platform for the stella
on discord or slack or anything like
that yet
did you have a follow-up yoshi
oh you know no that's totally fair yeah
i appreciate that response thanks thanks
man
good question peter i know you i know
you've got to get going thank you so
much for
for coming by this has been great this
is a great conversation i hope this is
the start of of many
many conversations and i'd love to talk
with you more about how
how we can work with you and you can
work with us and i think
again there's a lot of overlap in what
we're doing obviously so our communities
probably have a lot in common
and i know i know kira i know for
example is is a member of
both our communities so there's a lot of
overlap so i think we could
we can work together every time i see
that sun in the background i get excited
in the zoom room so yeah
you guys are you guys are lucky yeah and
then and uh you know i just want to tip
my hat off for
for you brett for everyone here for
building such a great community
um you know it seems quite strong and
like i said i think it's really
important that
john has a community foundation for his
ideas so they can flourish
because they are like not the most
accessible sometimes to a lot of people
because he
uses all these words so having a
community that can kind of like
educate people on it and on board them i
think is going to be quite helpful
yeah absolutely and of course you know
you know anyone from your community is
welcome to hang out here so uh
if they want a place to shoot the shit
of it and and you know we we've tried
you know to
to to maintain a non-toxic atmosphere
and we're very
attuned to that so that's uh so so
that's something
i i think we've been pretty lucky not to
have too much of that
uh here so so yeah we would
love to yeah love to have those people
there and thank you everyone for the
great questions as always and for being
here
uh remember we have a calendar and the
announcements uh
pinned in our in the announcements
channel is a link to our google calendar
and uh we also have our youtube channel
the awakening from the meaning crisis
discord
so please uh join and subscribe this q a
will be up
as with every other q a so if you miss
one you can go back and please like
like and subscribe so thanks everyone
for being here and thanks again peter
this has been great
awesome thank you brett thank you
everyone
take care thank you thank you for being
here